Guide to the Tamar R. Stone papers, 1998-2019 RL.11258
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Tamar R. Stone papers
1998-2019
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stone, Tamar R.
RL.11258
10 Linear Feet
Tamar Stone is a book artist whose one-of-a-kind works are made from fabric with embroidered text. This collection contains her book drafts, research materials, fabric and embroidery samples, book mock-ups, exhibition catalogs, press clippings, and correspondence with book dealers and collectors. The majority of the collection consists of documentation of the production of her Corset Books and her Bed Books.
Biographical / Historical
Tamar Stone is a New York-based book artist who has been active since the 1990s. Her work explores issues of women's appearance, self-esteem, restrictions, and assimilations. Each of her unique works are in the form of either a corset or a bed with the text of stories stitched into the fabric.
Stone holds a BFA in photography from Pratt Institute, and an MFA in film production from NYU. Her works are held by many academic libraries, as well as The New York Public Library, The Museum of Modern Art and The Victoria and Albert Museum.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Tamar R. Stone papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 2014-2019.
Collection Overview
The collection consists of materials related to Tamar Stone's work as a book artist including fabric samples, embroidery samples, book mock-ups, color photographs of works in progress, book drafts, research materials, exhibition catalogs, press clippings, and correspondence with book dealers and collectors. The majority of the collection documents the production of Stone's Corset Books and Bed Books.
Arrangement
Arranged into series for Bed Books, Corset Books, and other materials. The bed book and corset book materials are arranged chronologically by work.
Artists' books; Feminism in art.; Furniture in art.; Underwear in art.; Artists' books by women; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture -- Book designers' mock-ups
- Corset Books, 2000-2015
  Scope and Contents
  Many of the files on individual works contain color slides and photographs, fabric and embroidery samples, research and correspondence.
  - Pink Corset Book (Corset Book #1), 2000 (Box 1, Box 7)
    General
    Box 1: Pink Corset Book documentation Box 7: Pink Corset Book dummy
  - The Vital System, Good Sense, Little Beauty (Corset Book #2), 2000 (Box 1)
  - The Rational Corset Body (Corset Book #3), 2002 (Box 1)
  - To Make Her Look Her Best (Corset Book #4), 2002 (Box 1)
    "White corset book"
  - Childhood Comfort (Corset Book #5), 2003 (Box 1)
  - Gracefulness of Motion is Delightful (Corset Book #6), 2003 (Box 1)
    "pink child vest book"
  - What to Wear Vol. 1 (Corset Book #9), 2004-2005 (Box 8)
  - C is for Curvature (Corset Book #10), 2005 (Box 8)
  - The Upholstered Cage (Corset Book #11), 2005 (Box 8)
    Includes slides and dummy.
  - What to Wear Vol. 2 (Corset Book #12), 2006 (Box 8)
    All working files for this piece are at the Beineke Library along with the piece itself.
  - To Ensure Grace for Her (Corset Book #13), 2006 (Box 8)
  - Society's Corset (Corset Book #14), 2007 (Box 8)
  - Causes of Female Influence (Corset Book #15), 2007; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Health, Strength, Grace, and Symmetry, Vol. 1 (Corset Book #16), 2007 (Box 8)
  - Health, Strength, Grace, and Symmetry, Vol. 2 (Corset Book #17), 2007; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Individual Design Report (Corset Book #18), 2008 (Box 8)
  - Dress Versus Woman (Corset Book #19), 2010; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Mechanics of Beauty (Corset Book #20), 2011-2012; 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Caution and Counsel (Corset Book #21), 2012-2014; 4 folders (Box 9)
- Bed Books, 2003-2017
  - He Said She Said (Bed Book #1), 2003 (Box 3)
  - Household Comfort (Bed Book #2), 2004 (Box 3)
  - Asylum Institution Sanitarium (Bed Book #3), 2004 (Box 3)
  - A Case of Confinement (Bed Book #4), 2005 (Box 3)
  - Brought to Bed (Bed Book #5), 2006 (Box 3)
  - It's Where I Am Now (Bed Book #6), 2006-2007 (Box 3)
  - Taking to Bed (Bed Book #7), 2007 (Box 3)
  - Cure Bed (Bed Book #8), 2008; 3 folders (Box 8)
    Includes research, correspondence, print and embroidery samples, and color photos.
  - A Very Safe Place (Bed Book #9), 2009 (Box 3)
  - This is the End of a Long Tedious Journey (Bed Book #10), 2010 (Box 3)
    Oregon Trail/Frontier
  - Things Girls Like To Do (Bed Book #11), 2010-2011 (Box 3)
    Child housework
  - His Thanks Was Enough (Bed Book #12), 2013 (Box 9)
    Civil war cot
  - A Useful Domestic Exercise (Bed Book #13), 2007-2015 (Box 9)
  - The Bronte Bed (Bed Book #14), 2015-2016 (Box 9)
  - But Didn't Sleep Much (Bed Book #15), 2013-2017 (Box 9)
- Paper Books, 1998-2007
  - to exert (as oneself), 1999
    - To exert-as oneself (8 folders) (Box 2)
    - To exert-as oneself (dummy) (Box 5)
  - your/my insecurities are my limbs, 1998
    - Your/ my insecurities are my limbs (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Dolls on the Road, 2007
    - Dolls on the road (Box 3)
- Publicity, Catalogs, and Artists' Books, 1992-2019
  - Priscilla Juvelis, Inc. (Box 3)
  - Works in progress, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Publicity and catalogs, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Artist's books by various artists, 1992-1996 (Box 6)
  - Publicity, sales, shows, 2016-2019; 3 folders (Box 9)